Hugo Gernsback Papers
Hugo Gernsback Papers
- Writings
  - Articles
    - Radio-Electronics editorials, 1963-1965; undated; handwritten drafts, clippings of published versions; some also have related clippings, photographs, etc.; 9 folders (Box 31)
    - Radioelectronics in 1980, in Radio-Electronics, Jul 1954; 25th anniversary of magazine (Box 31)
    - Recent aerial developments, in Electrical Experimenter, Jun 1919 (Box 31)
    - Richtung elektronik - junger Mann! [Go electronic, young man!],in Radio Service, 1952 (Box 31)
    - Round trip to the moon, in American Weekly, Apr 1955 (Box 31)
    - Science fiction plus editorials, 1952-1953; handwritten drafts, typed drafts, clippings of published versions (Box 31)
    - Science fiction that endures, 1961; handwritten draft, noted as written for the 35th anniversary of Amazing Stories (Box 31)
    - Science and Invention editorials, 1920-1929; first folder has list of dates/titles; reproductions and photocopies; 4 folders (Box 31)
    - Science and Invention editorials, 1920-1929; originals (Box 38)
    - Science and Invention editorials, 1921; 1924,; undated; reproductions only (Oversize 3)
    - Science Wonder Quarterly editorials, 1929; list and vol. 1 no. 1 only (Box 31)
    - Science Wonder Stories editorials, 1929-1930; first folder has list of dates/titles; formats include originals, reproductions, and photocopies; 3 folders (Box 31)
    - Se construiran baterias atomicas y opacaran era de la electricidad [Atomic batteries will be built and the age of electricity will be overshadowed], in Venezuelan newspaper, 13 May 1954 (Box 31)
    - A sensational radio invention, in Transistor Research Bulletin, Jun 1954; reprint of 1924 editorial with added commentary (Box 31)
    - Sex publishing, 1958; typescript, noted as "article for Encyclopedia of Sexual Behavior" (Box 32)
    - Sexology articles, 1952; 1954-1955,; 1958,; 1961-1963; most are handwritten drafts, no published items; includes several film reviews; 11 folders (Box 32)
      Articles are: Announcing intimate questions (1963); Congolese rape of the Belgians (1961); Genealogy of Sexology (1955); Hands (1958); Last Year at Marienbad [review] (1962); Lolita [review] (1962); Male sexual decline (1952); Sex psychosemantomania (1954); Sodom and Gomorrah [review] (1963); A study in vicarious sex (1962). There is also one folder of article ideas.
    - Short Wave Craft editorials, 1930-1936; first folder has list of dates/titles; formats include originals, reproductions, and photocopies; 3 folders (Box 32)
    - Short Wave and Television editorials, See Writings by others: Short Wave and Television guest editorials
    - Signaling to Mars, in Modern Electrics, 1909 (Box 32)
    - Suspended gravitation, in Electrical Experimenter, Feb 1920 (Box 32)
    - Technocracy Review editorials, 1933 (Box 32)
    - Television editorials, 1928; vol. 1 no. 2 only; reproduction (Box 32)
    - Television News editorials, 1931-1933; includes list of dates/titles; formats include originals, reproductions, and photocopies (Box 32)
    - Television and the telephot, in Modern Electrics, Dec 1909 (Box 32)
    - Television in USA, in Radio Service [in German], 1952 (Box 32)
    - Two-wheeled autos, in American Weekly, Nov 1955 (Box 32)
    - Vest-pocket seven-tube superhetero-ultradyne (writing as Mohammed Fips), in Radio-Craft, May 1933 (Box 32)
    - Westinghouse recollections, in Engineering Contours vol. 5 no. 1, Jan 1960; includes full issue (Box 32)
    - What is sex? in Esquire, May 1956 (Box 32)
    - [Why I forecast the future], [1960?]; reprinted in 2 holiday advertising booklets from Knoxville Journal and Providence Journal (Box 32)
    - Wonder Stories editorials, 1930-1936; includes list of dates/titles; formats include originals, reproductions, and photocopies; 3 folders (Box 32)
    - Wonder Stories Quarterly editorials, 1930-1933; first folder has list of dates/titles; formats include originals and photocopies; 3 folders (Box 32)
    - A writing machine that responds to the voice, in Electrical Experimenter, Apr 1916 (Box 33)
    - Unidentified editorials, circa 1945 (Box 33)
  - Books
    - Collected works of Mohammed Ulysses Fips, 1986 (Box 33)
    - Experimental electricity course, with H.W. Secor, 1916 (Box 33)
    - Experimental electricity course, with H.W. Secor, 1918 (Box 33)
    - Experimental electricity course, with H.W. Secor, 1919 (Box 33)
    - Ralph 124C 41+, first edition, 1925; hardback, published by The Stratford Company (Boston) (Box 33)
    - Ralph 124C 41+, second edition, US, 1950; hardback, published by Frederick Fell (New York); forewords by Lee de Forest and Fletcher Pratt (Box 33)
    - Ralph 124C 41+, second edition, UK, 1950; paperback, published by Fantasy Books / Withy Grove Press (London) (Box 33)
    - Ralph 124C 41+, Utopia-Großband Nr. 52, 1957; digest-size German publication, with forewords by Forrest Ackerman, Walter Ernsting, and Gernsback; includes extra covers and note from Walter Ernsting, "Please sign the books and forward to Forry [Forrest Ackerman]. Keep the covers for own use. WE." (Box 33)
    - Ralph 124C 41+, Crest edition, 1958; paperback, published by Fawcett World Library (Chicago); foreword by Fletcher Pratt (Box 33)
    - Ralph 124C 41+, 1911; reprints of excerpts as published in Modern Electrics (Box 34)
    - Ralph 124C 41+, photoreproductions of illustrations (Box 34)
    - Ralph 124C 41+, preface to second edition; handwritten draft and typescript (Box 34)
    - Wireless course, with A. Lescarboura and H.W. Secor, 1915; red softcover (Box 34)
    - Wireless course, with A. Lescarboura and H.W. Secor, 1915; blue hardcover, bound upside-down (Box 34)
    - Wireless course, with A. Lescarboura and H.W. Secor, 1921; red hardcover (Box 34)
    - Wireless course, 12th edition, with A. Lescarboura and H.W. Secor, 1923; black softcover (Box 34)
    - The wireless telephone, 1st edition, 1910; dark blue hardcover (Box 34)
    - The wireless telephone, 2nd edition, 1911; beige paper covers; includes reproduced front matter pages (Box 34)
  - Forecast
    Forecast was Gernsback's annual holiday booklet, in which he laid out his science and technology predictions for the coming year. These were often covered in newspapers and magazines, with varying degrees of seriousness (see Memorabilia: Clippings about Gernsback, above). For most years, the material includes handwritten drafts, photographs, clippings used as reference, layouts, and final published booklets.
    - Forecast, 1952-1955; 4 folders (Box 34)
    - Forecast, 1956-1966; 11 folders (Box 35)
    - Forecast, 1966; layout material (photos, illustrations, etc.) (Box 38)
  - Forewords and prefaces
    - Illustrated Sex Atlas, "The reason for this book", 1962; handwritten draft (Box 35)
    - Television [book], 1927 (Box 35)
  - Letters to the editor, all clippings, unless otherwise noted
    - Advertising Age, on pay television, Jun 1955 (Box 35)
    - LIFE, on the mechanical bed, Dec 1945 (Box 35)
    - Newsweek, on mooring of dirigibles, Jul 1951 (Box 35)
    - Popular Science, on electric harpoon, Apr 1953 (Box 35)
    - Scientific Monthly, on the Schuss-yucca, Nov 1952 (Box 35)
    - Twilight Zine (MIT SF Society), 1961; handwritten draft only (Box 35)
    - Unasked Opinion (FAPA #62), 1952; includes transcription of Gernsback's speech at WorldCon X (Box 35)
  - Manuals
    - Official auto-radio service manual [and] complete directory of all automobile radio receivers, full installation and service guide, 1935; edited and published by Gernsback (Oversize 9)
    - Official radio service manual and complete directory of all commercial wiring diagrams, [1931?]; edited and published by Gernsback; includes several supplements (Oversize 9)
    - Official radio service manual [and] complete directory of all 1931-1932 radio receivers, edited and published by Gernsback; includes several supplements (Oversize 10)
    - Official radio service manual [and] complete directory of all 1933-1934 radio receivers, edited and published by Gernsback (Oversize 11)
    - Official radio service manual [and] complete directory of all 1934-1935 radio receivers, edited and published by Gernsback (Oversize 11)
    - Official short-wave radio manual: Complete experimenter's set building and servicing guide [and] full directory of all short wave receivers, 1935; edited and published by Gernsback (Oversize 12)
  - Poetry and music
    - Rǒd, Weis, Blo: Marche Luxembourgeoise, 1901-1903; published sheet music, reproductions, related clippings (Oversize 3)
    - Rǒd, Weis, Blo: Marche Luxembourgeoise, [1901-1903]; published sheet music (damaged) (Oversize 1)
    - Spring poem [humorous], 1907; typescript carbon (Box 35)
  - Speeches
    - Concrete science fiction, Eastern Science Fiction Association, 1961-1962; typescript and 2 copies as published in Telefiction Annual (Box 35)
    - Evolution of radio, Radio Club of America, 1960; as printed in their Proceedings (Box 35)
    - Fifty years hence, Henry Ford Museum, 5 Apr 1957; typescript (Box 35)
    - "Ford Museum slides", 5 Apr 1957; presumably accompanied speech (Box 35)
    - Future of radio, RCA Institute, 19 Dec 1930; typescript carbon (Box 35)
    - Future of radioelectronics, Purchasing Agents Association, 12 Apr 1955; typed draft with corrections (Box 35)
    - Future transportation, Engineering Society of Detroit, 1955; handwritten draft, typescript, related clippings (Box 36)
    - Impact of science fiction on world progress, WorldCon X, 1952; typescript (Box 36)
    - [Lescarboura testimonial dinner], 1961; handwritten draft, typescript carbon (Box 36)
    - "NYU slides", Apr 1958; lantern slides, presumably from a speech at New York University (Box 40)
    - Prophets of doom, MIT Science Fiction Society, 1963; typescript (Box 36)
    - Science fiction vs reality, MIT Science Fiction Society, 1960; typescript, galley proofs, illustrative photographs (Box 36)
    - Your electronic future, National Electronic Distributors Association, 1958; typescript, typescript carbon (Box 36)
  - Stories
    - Scientific adventures of Baron Munchausen, original pages from serialization in Amazing Stories, with handmade cover (Box 36)
    - Scientific adventures of Baron Munchausen, photocopied set (Box 36)
    - Scientific adventures of Baron Munchausen, reproductions of scattered pages (Box 36)
  - Miscellaneous
    - Christmas magazines, 1944-1946; 1949,; 1966; humorous annual publications, e.g. Radio-Cracy, Quip, Newspeek (Box 36)
    - Documentation of the learn-while-you-sleep method, 1950; printed brochure, illustrative photograph (Box 36)
    - Evolution of modern science fiction, 1952; typescript drafts, published booklet; appears to be a bibliography of science fiction stories published in Gernsback's various magazines (Box 36)
    - Inventing as a business, 1933; typescript with printed cover (Box 36)
    - Know yourself: Life mysteries explained, 1938-1939; Gernsback was presumably the editor; 4 issues in 2 folders (Box 36)
    - Letter announcing new magazine, 1961; handwritten draft; magazine described as digest of science for the layman (Box 36)
    - "Magazine of Fantasy and Science Fiction" endorsement, Sep 1957; printed on inside front cover; 2 copies of full issue (Box 36)
    - Radio-Electronics news releases, written in third person, but as Gernsback was the editor and owner these are considered to be by him (Box 36)
    - Science Fiction Plus, 1952; humorous/parody booklet (Box 36)
    - Space travel: When and how, 1953; survey by Gerry de la Ree of "leading men of science and science fiction"; Gernsback is named as contributor (Box 37)
    - The wireless screech, 1909-1910; parody magazine (Box 37)
    - Miscellaneous, notes, fragments, etc. (Box 37)
  - Writings by others
    - Dunninger, Joseph, "The art of thought reading", 1956; 2 printed copies; Dunninger wrote for Science and Invention, among other monthly magazines; and some of his books (though not this one) were published by Gernsback (Box 38)
    - Fitch, Clyde, "The staccatone", 1924; includes second article on same topic, with no byline (Box 37)
    - Gibbs, Angelica, "Inertrum, neutronium, chromaloy, p-p-p-proot", 1943; reproduction of original New Yorker article, and several photoreproductions of a title page or cover indicating it was reprinted "compliments of Hugo Gernsback" (Box 37)
    - Herrold, Charles D., "90 miles with a one inch coil" in Modern Electrics (Box 37)
    - Kazantsev, Aleksandr, Пылающий остров [Burning Island], 1939; Russian edition hardback; signed and inscribed on title page to Gernsback as "father of modern science fiction" (Box 37)
    - Marlowe, A.C., "Wave form apparatus," in Modern Electrics, includes letter to editor (i.e., Gernsback) about hearing earthquake through radio (Box 37)
    - Moskowitz, Sam, "The origin of the term science fiction", Feb 1957; reprinted by Gernsback as small booklet; originally appeared in Magazine of Fantasy and Science Fiction (Box 37)
    - Pomeroy, Wardell, "An analysis of questions on sex", 1960; reprint from The Psychological Record; used letters to Gernsback's magazine Sexology as its data set (Box 37)
    - Radio & Television guest editorials, 1939; original clippings; authors are Dubilier, McNinch, Girardeau, Beverage (Box 37)
    - Short Wave & Television guest editorials, 1937; list of titles and original clippings; authors are Sarnoff, de Forest, Horn, Zworykin, Hogan, Reinartz, Goldsmith, von Ardenne, Farnsworth, Baird (Box 37)
    - Steckler, Larry, "Solder joint removal", undated; typescript drafts of chapter 3 of How to Build Anything Electronic (Box 37)
    - Wolff, Th. [Thomas], "Can man free himself from gravity?", undated; photocopy; translated from the German and published in Science Wonder Stories (Box 37)
    - Unknown, "Electronics Industry Hall of Fame", circa 1990; typescript (computer printout) draft, consisting of bios of numerous members of the EIHF; 3 folders (Box 37)